S2 Module 6: An Update on Folding with Albert Garreta
Nico: Welcome to this module
of the ZK Whiteboard Sessions.
I am Nico, I'll be today's host
and with me is Albert.
Albert: It's a pleasure to be here.
So, today we will be speaking
about folding schemes.
I'll review the definition of folding schemes
because as I understand, there's a
module where these are discussed already.
Nico: Absolutely. Module 14.
If you haven't seen it, go check it out!
Albert: So, yeah, we will review what they are
and then, I'll give an overview
of what has happened since the
Nova scheme was introduced in 2022.
And after that we will focus on one
of these schemes, namely Hypernova.
Nico: Sounds good.
Albert: All right. Let's get into it.
All right, so folding schemes.
So we deal with relations as usual.
And for us a relation will be a set of triples,
and there's pp, X and W.
And these are public parameters,
this is called an instance,
and this is the witness.
Nico: Okay. So can we think of these as
the public inputs and the private inputs?
Albert: Yes, exactly.
These are --
Sometimes they are called as public inputs
and sometimes they are called as instances.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And you always have
the public parameters there.
It's kind of annoying technique
when you want to be formal,
you have to write them everywhere,
but no one thinks of them in practice.
Okay.
So what's a folding scheme?
So a folding scheme for two relations,
R and Racc,
and this "acc" is an
abbreviation for accumulation.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: But we could also say R₁ or R₂.
It's an interactive protocol
between prover and verifier,
where the prover has two instance
witness pairs for rela --
has an instance witness
pair for the relation R and
an instance witness pair for the relation Racc.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So I'm going to assume
that the public parameters are
the same for the two relations for simplicity.
Okay. And the verifier knows the
parameters and the input, the instance.
Okay. And then the prover and
the verifier exchange messages.
So it's an interactive protocol,
and eventually they output
a new instance witness pair.
So X₃, W₃.
This is known to the prover that this is --
The verifier outputs only the parameters and this.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So --
And the prover also outputs
W₃, but it keeps it private.
Okay. So this is the syntax of a folding scheme.
And now we want to state some properties
so that when they are satisfied,
the folding scheme can be used for some
purposes that will become apparent now.
Nico: So tell me to move over.
Amazing.
Albert: Okay. So requirements here.
One, we want this to be complete,
and this means -- we say it is complete
if whenever the prover is honest,
whatever he is outputting
here, this belongs to Racc.
Nico: Maybe I should ask, what do you mean
when we say a triple belongs in a relation?
Albert: Yeah.
So the prover might claim
that X₁ is a valid instance.
A valid instance means --
So if someone comes and says X is a
valid instance for the relation R,
it means that they are claiming that there exists
a witness, such that this tuple belongs to R.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So you can think of, for
example, R could be an equation --
Nico: Yeah.
Albert: And the instance could be some
parameters, the coefficients of the equation.
And when --
In this example, saying that the instance is valid
means that there exists a
solution for the equation.
And the solution will be the witness.
Nico: I see.
Albert: So here is like the prover
has an equation, an instance
and it has a solution to
the equation, the witness.
And in here a similar thing, but
for a different type of equation.
Nico: I see. Okay.
Albert: And okay. So requirements.
If P is honest, if the prover is
honest, then this is in this relation.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: In the accumulated relation.
And then the second property, this
is called "perfect completeness".
Nico: Which is I guess similar to
our completeness in our SNARKs.
Albert: Yes.
Yeah.
Then the second property is "knowledge soundness".
And we will not get into the formal
definition of knowledge soundness.
I'll just provide the intuition of what it means.
And it means that, if for any
prover, malicious or honest,
if the output belongs to the accumulated relation,
well, more correctly,
it's: except with negligible probability
over the randomness of the interaction,
if the output belongs to the accumulated relation,
then the initial two instances were correct.
Nico: Correct means they were --
Albert: In the relations.
Nico: In their respective relations.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So this is not really the
definition of knowledge soundness.
It's much more complicated.
You have to --
You quantify over a prover and then
-- so you say that for any prover.
and yeah, for any prover there
exists a polynomial time algorithm,
an extractor that can rewind the prover
and interact with the verifier through rewinding.
And from this, it is able to obtain a witness
W₁, and a witness W₂ so that this holds --
Nico: Okay.
Albert: With certain probability.
Nico: So very similar to knowledge
soundness in the SNARK case.
Albert: Yeah. It is pretty much the same.
If you know the definition of
knowledge soundness of the formal one,
this one is pretty much the same one.
Nico: Okay. And why are these useful?
What do we do with this?
Albert: So first of all, let's
forget about known applications.
Let's just look at this, at folding.
So here we have --
Imagine that the prover wants to prove
that X₁ is valid and X₂ is valid,
meaning that it knows that there's
a witness or that this belongs to R.
There's a witness and this
belongs to R accumulated.
So this technique allows to reduce this
task, the task of proving this and this,
to the task of proving just this,
because of the knowledge soundness.
Right?
Nico: Right.
Albert: So if this step is relatively cheap,
you are kind of saving work to be done.
Nico: That makes sense.
Albert: You had two tasks and now you have
just one task by paying a small price,
assuming that this is to be done.
So that's apparent --
I think this makes it quite
apparent that folding has potential.
Nico: Absolutely.
And what do we use it for?
Albert: Yeah.
So a typical application of folding is for
IVC or "Incremental Verifiable Computation".
Nico: And I think this is
actually covered in Module 14.
Albert: Yes. Or "Proof Carrying Data".
Nico: What is Proof Carrying Data?
Albert: It's --
So Incrementally Verifiable Computation is a
technique where you have several prove tasks
and instead of proving this task, you
keep folding and folding and folding.
And every time you have an accumulated instance,
so every time you have say, X₃,W₃,
and you get a new proof task incoming,
you fold it with the accumulated
one, and so on, and so on.
And at each step, you prove --
you have the prover create a proof
that the folding was done correctly.
And in this way, when you are done with
doing this Incremental Verifiable Folding,
at the end, you can just prove the accumulated
instance, the folded instance, this one,
because the prover has been proving
that the folding was done correctly.
By verifying this last step, the verifier can be
sure that all the previous steps were correct.
All the --
All the previous steps were correct,
and the instances that appeared in the
folding in the previous steps, were correct.
Nico: Because we have a cascade, I guess.
Like if this is right, then these two were right.
Albert: Yes.
And if this itself was one of these --
Albert: Exactly. Yeah.
Nico: We can -- Okay.
Albert: And if you --
You can picture IVC somehow as a
line where this is the accumulated.
Nico: I remember Justin Drake
drawing something similar.
Albert: The accumulated line.
And at each step there's a
non-accumulated instance coming in.
So this is from R.
Yeah.
You take R and R accumulated,
you get R accumulated.
Then you take R, R accumulated,
you get R accumulated, and so on.
And PCD is a generalization of this idea
where instead of just having a line,
you have an arbitrary, basically graph.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So you might have --
Nico: Many things.
Albert: Yeah. Some kind of tree.
Nico: Coming into each other.
Okay.
Albert: In here you have --
And then in the leaves you might have R.
Nico: I see.
Albert: Okay. Yeah.
But for the details, people
should check the module 14.
Nico: Module 14. Yeah.
So Nova from Module 14 is a folding scheme.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Or uses a folding scheme?
Albert: It is a folding scheme.
Nico: Okay. What has changed since?
Albert: Yeah. Let's discuss this.
Okay.
So now let's see what happened
since 2022, when Nova was published.
So Nova was a very influential paper.
A lot of work has come after it.
So let's see.
There's different lines of work, and each
line of work addresses different aspects.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So yeah, we have Nova from 2022.
And Nova has some limitations,
or it has very nice properties,
but there are also things that
can be seen as limitations.
Nico: I mean, we always want more anyway.
Albert: Yeah.
So one thing is that, if you try to
do Nova in a higher degree setting,
so Nova works for R1CSs that are degree 2.
If you want to use a similar idea for degree
10, then you have a quadratic blowout.
You have lots of cross
terms, like 100 cross terms.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And that is problematic.
So a way of addressing this issue
came with the paper, Hypernova.
Hypernova has other nice properties that I'm
not sure the purpose was to address --
to get those properties,
but it does have them.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So yeah, Hypernova, there's no
error terms, which is very nice because,
for example, in Nova, another --
another problem in Nova possibly
comes when you have to commit to
the error term, because the error term
has entries of arbitrary size which --
And this can be very expensive if you are using --
Nico: So just the process of
committing is expensive. Okay.
Albert: Yes. Committing to a vector of size --
whose entries have arbitrary size with
Pedersen commitments is very expensive.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And that is an issue.
So there is a line of work that addresses this.
So Hypernova addresses this actually,
because there's no error terms,
but addressing this issue,
there's also Mova and Protogalaxy.
So Mova --
Maybe I should write Protogalaxy first.
Protogalaxy is from 2023.
It does several things.
I'll talk about Protogalaxy in a minute.
Let me just start with Mova,
because it's simpler conceptually
and what it brings to the table is simpler.
So Mova is just a variation that we
published recently where we show that
it is not necessary to commit to the error
term in Nova. The commitment is superfluous.
That's what we show in Mova.
And this addresses a big
computational bottlenecking in Nova.
But as I said, Protogalaxy already does this.
Nova is kind of a particular case of
a variation of Protogalaxy anyway.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Okay.
Then there's other schemes
for higher degree constraints.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Or for different
types of arithmetizations.
For example, there's Sangria
by someone named Nico.
Nico: Yeah. I'm familiar with this guy.
Albert: Which deals with Plonkish constraints.
Plonkish constraints are -- in
practice, they are degree 2 or 3.
Albert: So it could also deal with
Plonkish constraints of arbitrary degree.
But one might have the same
issues as Nova in that case.
Nico: Absolutely.
Albert: And then there's Protostar
and Protogalaxy, which are wide --
You could say in simplistic terms that Protostar
and Protogalaxy are wide generalizations of Nova
for not only relations of very
high degree, but also protocols.
And there's another thing to
consider when you do folding,
which is whether you can fold different circuits,
which in the terminology of R1CSs
corresponds to having different matrices.
All these schemes do not support,
do not have this capacity.
So you are always bound to fold R1CSs
or whatever relation you have with
the same structure, so to speak.
There's KiloNova, which is an extension
of Hypernova that addresses this issue
and allows to fold where
the matrices are different.
And then all these schemes use elliptic curve
commitments, which present several issues.
There's several things that are undesirable.
Nico: So I guess you said
the cost was the problem?
Albert: The cost can be a problem sometimes.
There's also the problem
that if you want to do IVC,
when you have the prover proof that
the folding was done correctly,
then you have an issue because you
have to prove that some elliptic
curve operations were performed correctly.
Nico: Yes.
Albert: And then you are either
doing wrong field arithmetic
or you have to use cycles of
curves, which is a headache,
and it's also expensive. Yes.
Nico: I think Justin Drake
addresses it in the Nova module.
Albert: Yeah.
And another issue is that it bounds
you to the context of KCG-based SNARKs.
Nico: Right.
Albert: If you want to use --
To work over a small prime
field, you are kind of out of --
The possibility is not really there,
because here you are using elliptic curve
commitments and you need a big field.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So addressing these problems,
there's two new works from this year.
One is "Accumulation without homomorphism",
which describes a folding scheme where the
commitments are Merkle tree commitments.
Nico: So they use hash functions only?
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: You can probably replace the hash
functions by some other vector commitment,
but I think the idea is to use hash functions.
And in this case, there's really
no homomorphism being used,
which is completely different to
what's been the common trend before.
And then there's LatticeFold, which is
an analog of Hypernova for lattices.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And it kind of uses
homomorphic commitment schemes.
It uses the Ajtai commitment scheme,
which is homomorphic in some sense.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: It has some limitations.
There's some homomorphicity in
there, but there's some caveats.
Nico: Okay. So to --
I'm trying to get a representation of your map,
the ideas were: go beyond
R1CS, deal with cross terms,
you said, and get rid of elliptic curves, maybe,
or the cost of committing.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Very nice.
Should we dive into one of
these topics in particular?
Albert: Yeah. I wanted to discuss Hypernova --
Nico: Cool.
Albert: Because of several reasons.
It's an influential paper, it
has influential works beyond it
and even outside of the context of folding,
Hypernova deals with some ideas that
are, I think, in my opinion, very nice
and used in papers outside
of the context of folding.
So I think it is a very nice protocol
to look at when you get into this area.
Of course, after Nova.
So in Hypernova, R is the committed R1CS relation.
Nico: How is that different to regular R1CS?
Albert: So in folding, you usually take your
relation, the relation you really want to fold,
and you transform it into a
committed version of the relation.
And this just means that you add a commitment
to the witness in the public instance pair
Nico: Okay.
Albert: In the public instance part of the tuple.
And the accumulated relation is the
committed linearized R1CS relation.
Yeah. Committed linearized R1CS.
And let's see what all this means.
Before I move on, here I used R1CS,
but in the Hypernova paper,
the Hypernova deals with CCSs,
which, as I mentioned previously, CCS
is a high degree generalization of R1CS.
Nico: So can we imagine it being R1CS
with just more than three matrices?
Instead of being A, B, C, we can
have A, B, C, D, E, F and plenty more.
Albert: Yes. So there's more terms, more summands,
and each summand has possibly more
than a multiplication of two matrices.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So it could look like this.
A₁Z, A₂Z.
Nico: Right.
Albert: Oops.
A₃Z plus B₁Z B₂Z plus --
And then here you might have
four Hadamard products and so on.
Nico: Okay.
And so R1CS is like the simple version of this.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: And so now what is
the this linearized version?
Albert: Yeah. Let's first write what R is exactly.
Nico: Okay. Yes.
Albert: So as we saw, we said, then relations
are triples of public parameters, instances
and witnesses.
And in this case, the public
parameters are a field,
three matrices and then some size parameters.
So A, B, C are matrices of size n times n.
Nico: Are they always square? n times n?
Or is it --
Albert: Yeah. They are usually square.
Nico: Okay, cool.
Albert: X is a vector x.
So just a vector x in this case.
And X is a vector of size l.
Nico: Okay.
And the witness is just a vector.
Albert: Of size F, l minus 1.
Oops.
n minus 1 minus l.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And the following key relation is
satisfied by the instance and the witness,
which is that A times the vector z,
Hadamard product, B times the vector
z is equal to C times the vector z,
where z is this vector in here,
1 and this vector in here.
Nico: Okay.
I guess, why do we call this committed
R1CS as opposed to just R1CS?
Albert: Right. This is just the R1CS relation.
Thanks.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And the committed
R1CS relation is exactly this.
But we add a commitment to the
witness in the public instance.
So let's add it.
So we have the relation, and now if it's
committed, let's write here "committed".
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Then it's exactly the same,
but in here we have commitment.
Okay? And --
So this commitment is the commitment to the
vector w for some fixed commitment scheme,
which in Hypernova is usually Pedersen or KZG.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And you do this all
the time in folding schemes.
You have a relation you are interested in
and you transform it into the
committed version of the relation,
where you simply add a commitment to the witness.
Nico: Okay.
Because that is useful for the folding scheme, or?
Albert: Yeah. The folding scheme really requires
you to commit to the witness for security reasons.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Okay.
So this is outside of the finishing.
Nico: Yes, yes, yes.
Albert: Okay.
So now let's see what the linearized R1CS.
So again we have triples and
the parameters are the same.
And the instance now looks as follows.
So we again have a vector x.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And then we have another
vector r, which I will write --
This is an evaluation point for a polynomial
and writing it with the arrow, even
though x and w are also vectors.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And then we have two
field elements VA, VB, VC.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And then we have the committed part.
We have a commitment.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And the witness is a vector.
And that's it.
I think I'm not forgetting anything.
Maybe if I forget something, I will add it later.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So r is in --
is a point with log(n) coordinates
where VA, VB, VC are field elements
x and this commitment is the same as in --
Nico: As before.
Albert: The original R1CS,
and w is the same as before.
All right. And then the key property
here is that -- is the following.
So the instance and the witness
are valid if the following holds.
So yeah, this will look a bit weird now,
but when I explain how a Hypernova works,
it will become clear why we
have what I will write in here.
Nico: Sounds good.
Albert: So we have the multilinear extension of A.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Let's discuss later what that means.
Nico: Sure.
Albert: Evaluated at r and summed
over all elements of this hypercube.
We will unpack this later.
Nico: Okay. I have many questions.
Albert: Yes.
And the multilinear extension
of z at y, this is equal to VA.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And then we have
the same for B, equal to VB,
and the same for C equal to VC.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Okay.
And of course we have that w is the commitment.
Nico: Oh. Same as before.
Albert: Yes. Yes.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Okay.
Nico: So all will become clear in a bit.
Albert: Yeah. It will.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: It will.
I'll leave this definition here so we can come
back to it when this makes sense
and see, okay, this makes sense.
So, yeah, let's unpack a bit what's going on here?
So for --
I will not define what a multilinear
extension is for that there's some module.
Nico: Yeah, absolutely.
There's the Sum-Check module,
where I think we cover this.
Albert: Okay. I just mentioned that if
you have a map from this set to a field,
then f(X) will denote the
multilinear extension of f.
Okay?
Nico: Yeah.
Albert: And I'll be calling this
the hypercube of dimension m.
Nico: Okay. Fancy naming.
Albert: Yeah. Very fancy
name for a very simple thing.
Nico: It's just all the ones and zeros.
All the combinations of
zeros and ones. Is that it?
Albert: Yes, exactly!
Nico: Okay.
Albert: All vectors of size m with binary entries.
Albert: But hypercube is shorter. Right? So --
Nico: Yeah. And so is cool.
Albert: Even though it's fancy,
it's convenient sometimes.
Okay.
So an important property that is
usually needed when dealing with
multivariate or multilinear polynomials,
or polynomials in general in ZK is
this Schwartz–Zippel lemma, which in this case
we only needed four multilinear polynomials.
So if g(X) --
Oh, and this is a polynomial on n variables.
Nico: Okay.
So the X here is actually a bunch of small x's?
Albert: Yeah. Yeah.
Nico: Okay. I see.
Albert: I want to avoid writing
arrows everywhere all the time.
Nico: Sure.
Albert: Yeah.
And it is multilinear polynomial,
as the name indicates.
So if g(x) is multilinear
and r is sampled randomly uniformly in Fᵐ,
then the probability that g(r) is
0 is at most 1 over f -- the size of f.
Nico: Okay.
So similar to what we had with our univariate
polynomials back in our zero testing, I think.
So the number of variables
doesn't affect this at all?
Albert: No, it does not.
Nico: Okay.
So how are we combining these things?
You said it would all make sense. I'm --
Albert: Yeah.
Nico: Looking forward to seeing it click.
Albert: Yeah. Let's do it.
So, as I mentioned before, Hypernova --
In Hypernova, you apply the first step of the
Spartan scheme, the Spartan SNARK from Setty.
So I think it would be nice to explain
this first step in the context of Spartan.
Nico: Sure.
Albert: So it's still going to take a while to
get to here, but we will get there eventually.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Okay.
So the Spartan scheme.
So the Spartan --
Spartan is a SNARK for R1CS relations.
And how does it work?
Let's say that P has parameters, an instance, and
a witness in R R1CS as was described previously.
So parameters are a field, the
matrices, and some dimensions.
X is just x.
So a vector of public instances
and the W is a vector of witnesses.
Okay. I'll leave this here.
And now the prover claims that AZ,
Hadamard product, BZ equals CZ.
So yeah.
It claims that AZ, Hadamard product, BZ equals CZ.
Is the Hadamard product clear what it means?
Nico: You can define it if you think it's helpful?
Yeah, absolutely.
Albert: It's the component wise
multiplication of two vectors.
So u, the vector u, say u with t components.
And you have vector v with t components.
Nico: And we'll do v₁ times u₁.
Albert: Yeah.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Then u Hadamard v
is u₁v₁, blah blah blah.
Nico: uₜvₜ.
Albert: uₜvₜ.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And yeah, notice that because
this is matrix-vector multiplication.
This is a vector. Right?
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And this is a vector too.
Nico: Yeah.
Also reminiscent of I think Justin's episode.
Albert: Okay.
So this definition applies here
because we have two vectors.
Nico: Cool.
Albert: Okay. Let's switch.
Nico: Oh, sorry. Yes.
Albert: So now we will transform this
claim into a claim about polynomials.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: But first of all, let's analyze
matrix-vector multiplications in polynomial terms.
Okay.
So let's look at A times z set.
By the way, here, z is (x,1,w).
Nico: Like before.
Albert: Yeah.
So let's just look at A times z.
Let's also forget about the structure of z.
Let's just think of z as one vector
instead of a concatenation of three.
And yeah. So A --
A is a matrix. Right?
So A has entries, it's n times n entries matrix.
So we can picture the entries like this.
But we can also look at A
as a vector in F n².
Right?
Nico: How would you do that?
Albert: Because there's n-squared entries.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So if we flatten it, we
get a vector with n-squared entries.
And if we look at A as such a vector, we
can consider the multilinear extension of A.
Nico: Right.
Albert: Which is A times -- not times.
A, and then there's variables.
I'll denote them.
Us Un² --
oh, sorry.
U log(n²).
Right?
Because when you take the
multilinear extension of a map,
the number of variables you have is the
logarithm of the size of the hypercube.
So here maybe it's to make it --
Maybe this makes it more clear.
So this -- there are m elements here.
Nico: I see.
Because we're combining all the ones
and zeros.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So yeah, A is a vector.
A is a multilinear polynomial
on log(n²) variables.
And this is 2 times log n.
Okay. So to build the multilinear
extension of A, we index --
So if we want to build a
multilinear extension of A,
we have to index the entries of A with
elements from the hypercube, right?
Nico: Yes.
Albert: So --
Nico: That makes sense.
Albert: A, w -- u, sorry.
So this is u,
is the sum of the entries of the vector. Right?
Nico: Right.
Albert: So I'll put a cloud here for now.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Times multilinear extension of the
equality function of this index times u.
Right?
And this is an index --
The index runs over the entries of this -- of
the hypercube of dimension log n-squared.
Nico: Right.
Because we said this. Okay.
Albert: Right?
Nico: Right.
Albert: But we can look at this hypercube
as hypercube of 2 log(n) dimension.
And we can look at this as the
direct product of two hypercubes.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And then we can think of this part
in here as indexing the rows of the matrix
and this part as indexing
the columns of the matrix.
Nico: Okay.
So if I look at these as --
Sorry, these as bits.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: These would tell me
the bit number of the row?
Albert: Yes.
Nico: And then same for the column?
Okay.
Albert: So we split this hypercube in two chunks.
This one and this one.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And then this expression in
here becomes the following thing.
So it's the sum over x in the first hypercube
and y in the second hypercube of Axy.
So Axy means the entry indexed by the column
represented by this element of the hypercube
and --
Sorry. Row.
And the column indexed by
this element of the hypercube.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And then there's the equality polynomial
multilinear extension of x,y evaluated at --
And now we look at u as --
We also split u into two tuples.
Nico: Okay. So --
Albert: X, Y.
So here we are writing u as X, Y,
where X is a tuple of log(n) variables.
Nico: And Y is also --
Albert: Yeah.
Y is a tuple of log(n) variables.
Okay.
And this gives us A(X,Y).
Nico: Okay.
So to summarize this step, what we've done
here is the multilinear extension of a matrix.
Albert: Yes.
And we've written it in a nice way
where we know what happens when we --
when you replace one part of the variables of
the multilinear extension with an
index for a row or for a column.
Nico: I see.
Albert: Yeah.
And notice that in particular,
if you take x, y here, of course,
we get that the multilinear
extension evaluated at (x,y) is --
Nico: The matrix.
Albert: Is the entry.
Nico: The entry that we wanted.
That makes sense.
I guess that's the important part.
Albert: Yes.
Okay.
So now that we understand
multilinear extensions of matrices.
Nico: We're getting one step closer to this!
Albert: Yes!
Nico: Right.
Albert: Slowly but steadily.
Okay. So now let's look at Az.
So Az is -- what is -- is a vector. Okay?
Nico: Right.
Albert: And what's say, the
i-th entry of this vector?
It's the sum, and let's say x-th entry of
the vector where x is in the hypercube.
Nico: So it's a number, but
we write it and it's binary.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: It's just one row. x-th row.
Nico: Right.
So if I wanted row two, I would
have -- You know one zero.
Albert: You would have 0, 0, 0, 0, 1. Right?
Nico: And then another zero.
Yeah. That would be number two.
Albert: Yeah.
Nico: Cool. Okay.
Albert: So the x entry of this vector is the
sum of the entries of the matrix A in the row x.
Nico: Yeah.
Albert: So sum over the column indices, times --
Nico: A little bit of linear
algebra in the head for our viewers.
Albert: Yeah.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Times entries in z. Okay?
But this is --
And we have this at each x.
Nico: Yeah.
Albert: At each x entry.
Albert: But this is the sum
over y in this hypercube.
So let me write Bⁿ' here for brevity.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And then we have the
multilinear extension of A(x,y)
and then multineal extension of Z(y).
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Right.
So let's write phi A of X to be the
math where you sum over this hypercube.
You keep this X as a variable.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And replace the y's by the entries
in the hypercube and multiply by --
Nico: Okay.
So phi of A is what we just said here.
Like when we plug in some X, it gives us that row.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Yeah.
So phi A of a specific X in the
hypertube is one of these rows.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Right.
So phi A of X, and it is a multilinear polynomial.
It's easy to see that it is multilinear.
Nico: Multilinear or multivariate?
Albert: Multilinear.
Nico: Oh, multilinear. Okay.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Yes.
It's the multilinear extension,
and that's our only variable.
Albert: Yeah. There's only this variable.
You can --
If you want to do it as an exercise, you can
write the multilinear extension expression,
the typical one for both of them,
multiply things together and you will see
that you get the multilinear polynomial.
Nico: I trust you.
Albert: So phi of A is the multilinear
extension actually of A times z.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Because it is a multilinear
polynomial on log n variables,
and at each entry of the hypercube you
get one of these entries of this vector.
So by definition, it is the
multilinear extension of A times z.
Nico: I see.
Ah, I think I see where we are going now.
Albert: We we are slowly approaching. Yeah.
Nico: Yeah.
Albert: So recall --
So now recall that P claims that
Az, Hadamard, Bz is equal to cZ.
Okay?
So this is an equality between vectors, right?
Nico: Yeah.
Albert: So this is sum of Axy Zy
times sum of Bxy Zy
minus sum of Cxy Zy equals
the zero vector on all entries.
Nico: Okay.
So here what you've done is
you've moved this to this side
and you've put it equal zero.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Okay. I see.
Albert: And this is an if and only if.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: But then remember that phi A(X) is
the multilinear extension of these vectors.
Nico: Right.
Albert: So if we consider --
So we can see that this holds if and only if the
following expression holds
over the whole hypercube.
And the expression is the following,
is phi A(X) times phi B(X) minus
phi C(X) equals 0 on all the hypercube.
Nico: So if instead of X we replace --
for if we test each values of X that is in this.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: We should get zero all the time.
Albert: Yes, exactly.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Why is the equivalence true?
Because if you replace X, the variable X,
by an element of the hypercube, you
precisely get one of these rows.
Nico: That makes sense.
Albert: So if it is zero, then
every, each one of these rows is zero
and the columns is also quite easy to see.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: All right. So --
Maybe let's switch.
Nico: Oh, sure.
Albert: Thanks.
All right.
So now let's say that the prover is going to
prove this instead of proving this initial claim.
Nico: Sure.
Albert: So write g(X) to be this thing here.
So this is g(X).
Which is a multivariate polynomial.
It's no longer multilinear.
Nico: Because we have this multiplication, right?
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: All right.
So now the prover claims that certain
polynomial g is 0 on the whole hypercube.
How can we check this?
Well, there is a technique called zerocheck
that allows to check for that.
Nico: Okay.
I think Justin also covers
it in the Sum-Check episode.
Albert: Okay. So I will not --
I'll just give the overall scheme
and I will not explain why it works,
but we need -- we need the syntax at least.
Nico: Sounds good.
Albert: So P and V run the
zerocheck protocol for g(X).
And to do this, V sends a random
point r with log n coordinates.
And now P is going to prove that g at r is zero.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Oops.
Not g at r but --
So now P and V run a Sum-Check for the
claim that the following expression holds,
which is that g of little x
and the sum runs over the hypercube.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Times the equality polynomial --
multilinear extension of the equality polynomial
evaluated at r and x is zero.
This is how you do a zero check.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: The verifier sends a random point,
and then you run a Sum-Check for this claim.
Nico: Okay.
And this is the Schwartz-Zippel thing
you were saying about earlier, right?
Albert: Yes.
If this is zero, then, except with negligible
probability, g vanishes on the whole hypercube.
Nico: And this is what we wanted.
Albert: Yes, exactly. g is this.
Nico: Yeah.
Albert: Okay.
Nico: Cool.
Albert: And the Sum-Check reduces the
initial claim, this, to the claim g of r.
g of r' is equal to v for
certain r' point and v.
And this r' and v are determined during
the execution of this Sum-Check.
Nico: That makes sense.
Albert: Okay. So --
So far we have reduced the initial claim about the
R1CS relation into a claim about
an evaluation of a polynomial.
Nico: Yeah.
Albert: Now the prover has to
prove that g of r' is v.
But g of r prime is phi A(r'),
phi B(r') minus phi C(r').
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Okay.
So now P provides values
VA, VB, VC to the verifier,
and it claims that phi A(r') is VA,
phi B(r') is VB, and phi C(r') is VC.
Nico: Are these the same that we have in here?
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Nice.
Albert: So V checks that
VA times VB minus VC is V.
Okay?
And now P is left to prove
that phi A(r') is VA,
phi B(r') is VB,
and phi C(r') is VC.
Nico: This looks suspiciously
close to what we have in here.
Albert: Yeah.
If we unpack the definition of
phi A, we precisely get this.
Nico: Where do we have it?
Oh, phi A defined here.
If we replace X by r'.
Albert: Yeah.
Nico: Got you.
If you replace X by r'
here, phi A, you precisely
get this expression with r' instead of r.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Okay.
Nico: So is it fair to say
that this Racc is actually --
We try to prove this, we do the zerocheck
and we leave the rest unchecked.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: So the prover wants to prove this.
Albert: Prover and verifier exchange messages.
They do all this, and they
are left with this claim.
Nico: Yeah.
Albert: Okay.
But this claim is precisely this.
So they are left with an instance
witness pair for this relation.
Nico: Nice.
Okay.
Albert: Okay.
So this is the first step of the Spartan protocol.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: The first step of the Spartan
protocol takes the initial claim
and reduces it to a claim about
belonging to this relation.
Nico: Okay.
So how does this relate to folding?
Why did we do all this?
Albert: Well, it is actually very
nice because this relation is very
easy to fold because it's
really a linear relation.
Right?
Nico: Why does that make it easy to fold?
Albert: Because when you fold,
the way folding usually is done is you take
a random linear combination of the witness.
And then in Nova, for example,
the relation is quadratic.
Nico: Yes.
Albert: And this introduces -- this causes
a mess because the relation is not linear.
So taking linear combinations of witnesses is
not compatible with your original equation.
Nico: That's why we had all
this error term situation.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: And -- okay.
Albert: But if your original
constraints are linear,
taking linear combinations of solutions gives
you solutions to the original constraint.
Nico: Right.
Albert: Without changing the constraint.
Could you maybe show us?
Albert: Yes.
Now, Hypernova, say we have an
instance from the committed R1CS.
So we have W and then we have pp, X',
W' in R linearized R1CS.
And everything is committed.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Let's forget about commitments.
And then what prover and
verifier do is the following.
P and V --
Okay. It's not exactly --
There's a small thing that has to
be done that I will explain later.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: But mostly Hypernova works as follows.
P and V run what? The protocol I just described.
Nico: So this whole zero check --
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Part.
Well, partial, I guess, zero check up to here.
Albert: Yeah.
Nico: I see.
Albert:
To transform this instance into
a linearized R1CS instance.
Into, let's call it X₀, W₀ in R linearized R1CS.
And now Prover and Verifier
are left with folding two
instance readiness pairs from the linearized R1CS.
Nico: Which is this thing?
Albert: Yes.
Albert: So let's write what they are.
There's X₀ -- X₀, r₀, VA₀, VB₀, VC₀
and x¹ or x' -- x', r',
VA', VB', VC'.
Nico: So here you're ignoring the commitments
just because we don't really need them or?
Albert: No. We should add the commitments here.
But I'm ignoring them for simplicity.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Or maybe I should add them.
Let's add them.
All right.
So commitment to witness w₀,
commitment to witness w'.
Okay. So there are two cases here.
Whether the evaluation point is the
same or whether it is different.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: I'm going to assume
that it is the same for now.
Nico: Sure.
Albert: And we will discuss
what happens if it is not.
Nico: Maybe we should keep this.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: It's been useful for
me at least for reference.
Albert: Yes, I delete this. Delete this.
Okay. So we know that these and these are true.
If and only if.
I'm gonna focus on the A part, but everything
applies to the other equation. Yes.
So we know that sum of A(r,y) Z₀(y) is equal to VA₀
and sum of A(r,y) Z'(y) is equal to VA'.
And here Z₀ is X₀, 1, witness 0.
Z' is x', 1, witness prime.
Nico: Right.
And here the sum is over what?
Albert: Over the hypercube.
Nico: Okay.
So as in our statement here. Absolutely.
Albert: Yes.
So folding now proceeds similarly as in Nova.
Verifier sends a random challenge,
random element, alpha in the field.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: And now notice that if you take a
random linear combination of Z₀ and Z',
then you keep the same identity with
the random linear combination if you
add a corresponding random
linear combination in here.
Nico: Right.
Because we can factor things. Right?
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Is that correct?
Albert: So we have that --
Nico: Actually, I'll move to the other side.
Albert: Yeah.
So it is very easy to see
that if these two things hold,
then the sum of A(r,y) times Z₀(y) plus alpha
Z'(y) is equal to VA plus alpha VA'.
Nico: So just to visualize, if we
distribute this, we have this sum up here.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Plus alpha times that sum.
Nico: And it's actually these results.
Okay, cool.
Albert: Yes.
So the accumulated witness
will come from the accumulated
Z₃, which will be Z₀ plus alpha Z'.
Nico: Right.
Albert: Which is X₀, 1 --
Nico: w₀.
Albert: w₀ plus alpha(X', 1, w').
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Okay.
So, yeah --
Nico: So we had --
These two are the same.
Albert: Yes.
Nico: These two we update like this.
Nico: These we've updated there.
Albert: Yeah. And --
Nico: What about the commitments?
Albert: The new value for --
The accumulated value for A is
going to be VA₀ plus alpha VA'.
Nico: Okay. Yeah.
Albert: And for the commitments,
commitment to the w₃ is just the
commitment to the linear combination
of the two witnesses we started with,
which can be computed using
the homomorphic property.
Nico: Okay.
So if I add two commitments together,
I get the commitment of the sum.
Albert: Yeah.
Nico: Cool.
So we did this protocol to go
from R1CS to linearized R1CS,
Albert: Yes.
Nico: Because it's very easy to do this.
Albert: Yeah.
Nico: Okay. And that's our folding scheme.
Albert: And the step that goes from R1CS into here
can be generalized to high degree
without paying too much of an overhead.
You just do a Sum-Check.
You do a similar reduction.
There's also the nice thing that
you don't commit to any error terms.
There's no error terms
appearing anywhere, actually.
Nico: Right.
Albert: Because when you actually do the
folding, you are folding a linear relation,
which is super simple to do.
Nico: Okay. Well, simple.
Albert: Yeah, well.
Nico: This part is simple,
but I think going down to
here was a bit, you know.
Albert: Yeah. But going down to here was the --
It was not folding the linear part. Right?
Nico: True, true, true, true.
Albert: Yeah.
There's one thing left, which
is when r₀ is not r'.
And Hypernova uses a really nice
trick to deal with this issue.
Nico: Cool.
So let's maybe wrap up how the
Hypernova folding scheme works
and then wrap up the whole module, maybe.
Albert: Okay.
So the Hypernova scheme folds CCS
instances into linearized CCS instances.
We wrote the scheme for instead of CCSs for R1CSs.
The way it works is first it uses a Sum-Check
and a smart way of expressing
the initial R1CS constraint in
terms of polynomials and in terms of a zerocheck.
So in terms of a claim about a polynomial,
multivariate polynomial
being zero on the hypercube,
and then use a zerocheck which uses
the Sum-Check to prove this claim.
And we saw that when you use
the zerocheck for this claim,
you end up with a so-called linearized
R1CS relation which looks like this.
And then we saw that if you have
two linearized R1CS relations,
it's very easy to fold them together.
You just send a random challenge and take random
-- take the linear combination of everything.
Nico: Okay.
Albert: Yeah, we left --
We make an assumption while describing
the scheme, which is a strong assumption,
you have to deal with the general case where
the two evaluation points are not the same.
The trick in Hypernova where this
is dealt with, it's really nice.
I recommend everybody to check it out.
Nico: Sounds good.
Albert: And yeah, that's
the overview of Hypernova.
Nico: Amazing!
Thank you very much!